<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>  <!-- Required for schema validation and schema-aware editing -->
<!-- <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?> -->
<!-- This third-party XSLT can be enabled for direct transformations in XML processors, including most browsers -->


<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- If further character entities are required then they should be added to the DOCTYPE above.
     Use of an external entity file is not recommended. -->

<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="info"
  docName="draft-link-v6ops-6mops.xml"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates="8585"
  submissionType="IETF"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">
  <front>
<title abbrev="6mops">IPv6-Mostly Networks: Deployment and Operations Considerations</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-link-v6ops-6mops"/>
    <author fullname="Jen Linkova" initials="J" surname="Linkova">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->
          <street>1 Darling Island Rd</street>
          <city>Pyrmont</city>
          <region>NSW</region>
          <code>2009</code>
          <country>AU</country>
        </postal>        
        <email>furry13@gmail.com</email>  
        <email>furry@google.com</email>  
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2024"/>
<area>Ops</area>
    <workgroup>IPv6 operations</workgroup>
    <keyword>ipv6</keyword>
    <keyword>slaac</keyword>
    <keyword>464xlat</keyword>
    <keyword>clat</keyword>
    <keyword>nat64</keyword>
    <keyword>pref64</keyword>
    <keyword>ipv6-only</keyword>
    <keyword>ipv6-mostly</keyword>


    <abstract>
 <t>
This document discusses an deployment scenario called "an IPv6-Mostly network", when IPv6-only and IPv4-enabled endpoints coexist on the same network (network segment, VLAN, SSID etc).
</t>

    </abstract>
 
  </front>

  <middle>
    
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
<t>
While most network operators initially deploy IPv6 alongside their existing IPv4 infrastructure, pure IPv6-only networks remain uncommon outside of the mobile carrier space. This dual-stack approach is seen as a necessary transition phase, allowing operators to gain experience with IPv6 while minimizing disruption.
</t>

<t>
However, dual-stack networks don't address the core problem driving IPv6 adoption: IPv4 address exhaustion. They still require the same amount of IPv4 resources as IPv4-only networks.  Even worse, this dual-stack approach often becomes a long-term crutch. Many applications still rely on IPv4, creating a chicken-and-egg problem: IPv6-only networks seem impractical with so many incompatible applications, yet applications continue to rely on IPv4 because IPv6-only networks are rare.
</t>

<t>
The less control a network operator has over devices and applications, the more difficult it is to break IPv4 dependencies and move to IPv6-only. This is particularly challenging in enterprise networks with legacy IPv4-dependent applications and public WiFi networks where operators cannot guarantee device compatibility.
</t>

<t>
To enable a gradual migration, operators need to identify which devices can function in IPv6-only mode and which cannot. Creating separate network segments for each type introduces complexity and scalability issues – a major hurdle to IPv6-only adoption.
</t>

<t>
A more desirable approach is to deploy so-called "IPv6-mostly" network that provides IPv4 on demand. This allows IPv6-capable devices to remain IPv6-only while seamlessly supplying IPv4 to those that require it.
</t>

<t>
This document explores the requirements, recommendations, and challenges associated with deploying IPv6-mostly networks in enterprise and public WiFi environments. While the principles discussed may be applicable to other network types, this document's focus remains on these specific use cases.
</t>
    </section>
      
      <section>
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
          RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
          interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
          all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>

<section anchor="term">
<name>
Terminology
</name>
<t>
This document reuses most of Terminology section from <xref target="RFC8925"/>.
</t>
<t>
Network segment: a link (VLAN, a broadcast domain etc) where hosts share the same IP subnet.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="overview">
<name>Solution Overview</name>
<t>

</t>

<section anchor="capable">
<name>IPv6-Only Capable Hosts</name>
<t>
</t>

</section>

<section>
<name>Coexistence of IPv6-Only and IPv4-enabled Hosts</name>
<t>

</t>
</section>

<section>

<name>Access to IPv4-only Destinations</name>
<t>
</t>

<section>

<name>NAT64</name>
<t>
</t>

</section>


<section anchor="v4only">
<name>464XLAT</name>
<t>

</t>

</section>

<section anchor="dns">
<name>Signalling NAT64 Prefix to Hosts</name>
<t>
Hosts running 464XLAT need to discover the PREF64 (the IPv6 prefix used by NAT64).
The network administrator SHOULD configure the first-hop routers to include PREF64 information in Router Advertisements as per (<xref target="RFC8781"/>) even if the network provides DNS64 (so hosts can use DNS64-based prefix discovery, <xref target="RFC7050"/>).
This is required as hosts or individual applications might have custom DNS configuration (or even run a local DNS server) and ignore DNS64 information provided by the network, so they can not use <xref target="RFC7050"/> method to detect PREF64.
In the absense of PREF64 information in Router Advertisements such systems would not be able to run clat, which would cause connectivity issues for all IPv4-only applications running on the affected device. 
As such device wouldn't be able to use the network-provided DNS64, access to IPv4-only destination would be impacted as well.
At the time of writing all major OSes supporting DHCPv4 option 108 and enabling clat automatically also support <xref target="RFC8781"/>.
Therefore providing PREF64 information in RAs can reliably mitigate the impact of custom DNS configuration on those systems.
</t>
<t>
Receiving PREF64 information in RAs also speeds up the clat start up time, so an IPv4 address and default route become available for applications much faster.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="dns64">
<name>DNS vs DNS64</name>
<t>
</t>

</section>

</section>

</section>

<section anchor="benefits">
<name>Solution Benefits</name>

<section anchor="vsds">
<name>Benefits Compared to Dual-Stack</name>
<t>
[note from furry@]: IPv4 saving, operation simplicity.
</t>
</section>


<section anchor="vsv6only">
<name>Benefits Compared to a Dedicated IPv6-Only Network</name>
<t>
[note from furry@]: scalability, easy for users, incrememntal migration
</t>
</section>


</section>

<section anchor="rollout">
<name>Incremental Rollout Considerations</name>
<t>

[note from furry@]:
- no safety net of HE, so many issues which have been hidden will become very much visible now

</t>

<section anchor="optin">
<name>Opt-In and Opt-Out Approach</name>
<t>
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section anchor="ops">
<name>Operational Considerations</name>

<section anchor="slaac">
<name>Address Assignment Policy</name>
<t>
[note from furry@] explian why SLAAC is mandatory currently
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="eh">
<name>Extension Headers</name>
<t>
[note from furry@] EH issue: permit at least ESP and Fragments
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="issues">
<name>Typical Issues</name>
<t>
This section discusses some typical issues which might be observed in IPv6-mostly networks.
Without safety net of IPv4 to fallback if IPv6 is broken, all potential network issues and IPv6 bugs become much more visible and impactful.
However implememtation bugs are mostly out of scope of this document, as such bugs would vary from network to network, depending on equipment and software used.
Instead this section focuses on issues caused by configuration, topology or design choices.
It should be noted that most of those issues usually pre-exist in dual-stack networks, but, as devices can fall back to IPv6, those problems are often remain unnoticed until IPv4 is taken away. 
The network administrators are advised to audit and monitor for the scenarios described below prior to migrate an existing network to IPv6-mostly mode.
</t>

<section anchor="nov6">
<name>Hosts with Disabled or Misfunctional IPv6</name>
<t>
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="ext">
<name>Network Extension</name>
<t>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="multip">
<name>Multiple Addresses per Device</name>
<t>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="gulla">
<name>Host Mobility and Renumbering</name>
<t>
If devices can move between network segments (VLANs) (e.g. if 802.1x with RADIUS-based VLAN assignment is used), it is recommended to reduce min and max Router Advertisement intervals to ensure that unsolicited RAs are sent as often as possible.
It is also recommended to decrease PIO lifetimes
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="frag">
<name>Fragmentation</name>
<t>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="traceroute">
<name>Representing IPv6 Addresses by CLAT</name>
<t>
</t>
</section>


</section>
</section>

    <section anchor="Security">
      <!-- All drafts are required to have a security considerations section. See RFC 3552 for a guide. -->
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
<t>
</t>
</section>

    <section anchor="privacy">
      <name>Privacy Considerations</name>
      <t>
This document does not introduce any privacy considerations.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="IANA">
    <!-- All drafts are required to have an IANA considerations section. See RFC 8126 for a guide.-->
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This memo does not introduce any requests to IANA.</t>
    </section>
    
    <!-- NOTE: The Acknowledgements and Contributors sections are at the end of this template -->
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6333.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6877.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7050.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7335.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8781.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8585.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8925.xml"/>
        <!-- The recommended and simplest way to include a well known reference -->
        
      </references>
 
      <references>
	      <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.1918.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6145.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7225.xml"/>

      </references>
    </references>
    
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
<t>
Thanks to  for the discussions, the input and all contribution.
</t>
    </section>
    
 </back>
</rfc>
